<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Semantic Web on J. Fernando Sánchez</title><link>https://balkian.com/tags/semantic-web/</link><description>Recent content in Semantic Web on J. Fernando Sánchez</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 10:24:52 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://balkian.com/tags/semantic-web/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>RDF Is Dead</title><link>https://balkian.com/p/rdf-is-dead/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 10:24:52 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://balkian.com/p/rdf-is-dead/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A big part of my research has been around vocabularies and semantic annotation.
And, to be honest, I&amp;rsquo;ve grown increasingly dissatisfied with the field.
To the point where I dread having to work on it.
Some day I will write about it in length, but today I&amp;rsquo;ve stumbled upon a post that covers the topic quite well: &lt;a class="link" href="https://terminusdb.com/blog/the-semantic-web-is-dead/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;The Semantic Web is Dead - &lt;del&gt;Long Live the Semantic Web&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (styling mine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, this section has really resonated with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="note"&gt;&lt;h1 id="academics-and-industry"&gt;Academics and Industry
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;The political economy of academia and its interaction with industry is the origin of our current lack of a functional Semantic Web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academia is structured in a way that there is very little incentive for anyone to build usable software. Instead, you are elevated for rapidly throwing together an idea, a tiny proof of concept, and to iterate on microscopic variations of this thing to produce as many papers as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In engineering, the devil is in the detail. You really need to get into the weeds before you can know what the right thing to do is. This is simultaneously a devastating situation for industry and academia. Nobody is going to wait around for a team of engineers to finish building a system to write about it in Academia. You’ll be passed immediately by legions of paper pushers. And in industry, you can’t just be mucking about with a system that you might have to throw away.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>